Okay, awesome. Okay, thanks for pointing this out. Sorry about that, everyone. So we have
好的，太棒了。好的，谢谢你指出这一点。对不起，大家。所以我们有...
now what are the rules for the GCR? Still mostly this class will be remote. All lecture
现在GCR的规定是什么？大部分课程仍然是远程授课。所有的讲座都是远程授课。
will be remote. This is what the department decided actually early on even before Delta
将是远程工作。实际上，这是部门在Delta疫情爆发之前就做出的决定。
variant and all exams will be remote. We'll have three midterms. There is no final. And
变种病毒，所有考试都将远程进行。我们将有三次期中考试，没有期末考试。而且
we have 17 discussion sections on Thursday and Fridays, four on Thursday, 13 on Friday.
我们在周四和周五有17个讨论小组，其中四个在周四，13个在周五。
Out of those, four will be in person. They will be on Friday and 30 will be remote. Now,
其中有四个将是面对面的。它们将在星期五进行，而其他30个将是远程的。现在，
please make sure because of that you have a working camera because you are going to
请确保你有一台工作正常的相机，因为你将要使用它。
have Zoom proctoring of exams and require section design reviews, working with your
进行Zoom监考以及要求进行部分设计审查，与您合作。
colleagues for the group projects, all requires to see each other and also screenshots. So
同事们对于小组项目都要求相互见面，并且还需要截屏。所以
goals of today lectures, it's an introductory lecture, obviously, is to try to figure out
今天讲座的目标是弄清楚，显然，这是一堂介绍性的讲座。
a little bit what is an operating system and in particular also what is not. And also I'm
一个操作系统是一种软件，它管理计算机硬件和软件资源，并提供给用户和应用程序一个统一的接口。操作系统负责协调和控制计算机的各种活动，例如文件管理、内存管理、进程调度和设备驱动程序等。
操作系统的主要功能包括：
1. 提供用户界面，使用户能够与计算机进行交互。
2. 管理计算机的硬件资源，例如处理器、内存和存储设备。
3. 提供文件系统，用于管理和组织数据。
4. 控制和协调应用程序的执行，包括进程调度和资源分配。
5. 提供网络功能，使计算机能够连接到其他计算机和设备。
操作系统不是应用程序。它是一种系统级软件，与应用程序不同，它不直接为用户提供功能，而是为应用程序提供运行环境和资源管理。操作系统是计算机系统的核心组成部分，它使得计算机能够运行各种应用程序，并提供了对硬件资源的抽象和管理。
going to say a few words about what makes operating systems so exciting. It's a while
我要说一些关于操作系统为何如此令人兴奋的话。已经有一段时间了。
and is actually probably one of the most exciting times to study and work on operating systems.
并且实际上，现在可能是研究和工作于操作系统最令人兴奋的时期之一。
And then we are going to talk a little bit more at the end about how does a class operate.
然后我们在最后会再多谈一点班级是如何运作的。
Please interactivity is important. Now I know that it's harder, especially with a webinar.
请注意互动性很重要。现在我知道这更难，尤其是在网络研讨会中。
I'm going to stop from time to time and look and take questions. And of course, please
我会不时停下来观察并回答问题。当然，请问有什么需要帮助的吗？
ask questions and notes because even while I am talking, other people could answer them,
请问问题和做笔记，因为即使我在说话的时候，其他人也可以回答。
you know, some of our TAs. So what is fundamentally an operating system? So one way to think about
你知道，我们的一些助教。那么，操作系统从根本上是什么呢？有一种思考方式是这样的：
the operating system is that is that software layer which runs on top of hardware of the
操作系统是运行在硬件之上的软件层。
hardware and provide support to the application. Right. What does that mean, providing support
硬件并为应用程序提供支持。对的。提供支持是什么意思？
to applications means that it makes it easier to develop applications and take advantage
对于应用程序来说，这意味着它使开发应用程序和利用其优势变得更加容易。
of the hardware capabilities. It also protects applications from each other. It provides
硬件能力的抽象化。它还保护应用程序之间的隔离。它提供了
security and authentication. So only the applications which should use the hardware and have access
安全和身份验证。因此，只有应该使用硬件并具有访问权限的应用程序可以使用。
to the data and also provide support for cooperation. There are applications which cooperate with
数据，并为合作提供支持。有一些应用程序与之合作。
each other. And obviously this is more and more expected today. We are in the age of
互联网和全球化，人们之间的联系和交流变得更加频繁和紧密。无论是在个人生活还是商业活动中，人们都需要与不同国家和文化背景的人进行交流。因此，相互理解和跨文化交流变得越来越重要。人们需要学习不同的语言和文化，以便更好地与他人沟通和合作。在当今世界，多语言能力和跨文化交际技巧已经成为一种竞争优势。
the internet. Right. And why do we care to provide support for applications? Well, because
互联网。对的。我们为什么要关心为应用程序提供支持呢？嗯，因为
most of the things you do online, you do through applications. That's it. Right. It's the most
大部分你在网上做的事情都是通过应用程序完成的。就是这样。对吧。这是最常见的情况。
is a way people interact with computers is that people are going to interact with the
人们与计算机互动的一种方式是人们将与计算机互动
virtual world. So a physical world, virtual world. Virtual world means applications. And
虚拟世界。所以一个物理世界，虚拟世界。虚拟世界指的是应用程序。而
also to drive home the point, here are some numbers about how the global mobile market
此外，为了强调这一点，以下是一些关于全球移动市场的数据。
size. And you can see it is huge. And actually even year over year, the growth is significant.
尺寸。你可以看到它很大。实际上，即使是年度增长也是显著的。
Right. 20% or more. Right. And it's again an application provides the abstraction, manages
正确。20%或更多。正确。而且这又是一个提供抽象化、管理的应用程序。
the resources, hardware resources. And it's achieving that through using a bunch of algorithms
资源，硬件资源。它通过使用一系列算法来实现这一目标。
for scheduling application or processes, providing access to resources from different concurrent
用于调度应用程序或进程，提供对不同并发资源的访问。
applications running at the same time. And security and many more. Okay. So right now,
同时运行的应用程序。还有安全性等等。好的。所以现在，
let's look again a little bit. Oh, there is a question here. What is now an exciting time
让我们再仔细看一下。哦，这里有一个问题。现在是什么时候最令人兴奋？
for starting working in OS? Yes, we are going to answer that later because the impact of
开始在操作系统中工作？是的，我们稍后会回答这个问题，因为这会对...产生影响。
the OS and the challenges are bigger than ever. That's a short answer. Okay. And here
操作系统和挑战比以往任何时候都更大。这是一个简短的回答。好的。然后呢？
it's again, it's not a problem during this lecture if you don't understand everything.
这又是一次，在这堂课上，如果你不理解一切，也不是问题。
This is, you know, we are in here to provide some kind of end to end feeling about what
这个，你知道的，我们在这里是为了提供一种端到端的感觉，让人明白什么
the operating system is doing. But the rest of the class, we are going to dive in and
操作系统正在做什么。但是，我们班的其他同学，我们将深入研究并
we are going to, you know, to look at all these aspects I'm going to touch during this
我们打算，你知道的，去看看我在这个过程中要涉及的所有方面。
lecture in more detail. So basically it's again, it's an application you want to run
讲座需要更详细的解释。基本上，这是一个你想要运行的应用程序。
an application, run a program and you have to run it on top of the hardware. Now, what
一个应用程序，运行一个程序，你必须在硬件之上运行它。现在，什么呢？
is a hardware consisting from? You have a processor which needs to execute the instructions
硬件由什么组成？你有一个需要执行指令的处理器。
to run your applications and you clearly have a memory, right? We store the data and store
运行您的应用程序，您肯定有内存，对吗？我们存储数据并存储
the program, you store the application code, right? So the processors read the instructions
这个程序，你存储应用代码，对吗？所以处理器读取指令。
and read the data and executes those instructions on the data and this is how your application
并读取数据并在数据上执行这些指令，这就是您的应用程序的工作方式。
is running. In addition to just memory, you have a cache to keep the most recent data
正在运行。除了内存之外，您还有一个缓存来保存最近的数据。
or the most accessed data around closer to the processor. So this is obviously for improving
或者将最常访问的数据更靠近处理器。所以这显然是为了提高
the performance. You have a page table and TLB translation, look at side buffers, this
表现。你有一个页表和TLB翻译，看看侧缓冲区，这个
is again, it's our mechanism for improving the performance. And besides that, you have
再次强调，这是我们提高性能的机制。除此之外，你还有什么问题？
a storage where you need to store the data, the program at rest, the processor and memory
一个需要存储数据的存储设备，程序处于休眠状态，处理器和内存。
are storing the data and run the program only when they are powered on. And obviously you
只有在通电时才能存储数据和运行程序。显然，你
have a lot of peripherals. You have displays, you have a mouse, you have network, you are
有很多外设。你有显示器，你有鼠标，你有网络，你是
connected to the internet and many more, right? So this is quite complex, right? So now the
连接到互联网和更多的功能，对吗？所以这相当复杂，对吗？那么现在的情况是这样的。
key here and they are connected, right? All of these pieces are connected. So the key
是的，这里的关键是它们之间的连接，对吗？所有这些部分都是相互连接的。所以关键是
here is basically how you are going to make easy and secure for the application to run
这里基本上是你要如何使应用程序易于运行和安全的方法。
on this hardware and also take advantage of the hardware capabilities. Okay. And many
在这个硬件上，并且充分利用硬件的功能。好的。还有很多
of these things you learn, like this is a machine structure in CX61C. And it's again,
关于这些你学到的东西，比如这是CX61C的机器结构。而且，它又是...
one of the main functionality of the operating system is to abstract away this hardware to
操作系统的主要功能之一是将这些硬件抽象化
the application. Okay. So let me do this next set of few slides and then I'll stop for
应用程序。好的。那么让我继续做下一组幻灯片，然后我就停下来。
questions. So one way to think about operating system is this like illusionist, right? And
问题。所以一个思考操作系统的方式就像是魔术师，对吗？而且
why is that? Because again, it's provide this kind of abstraction of the physical resources
为什么会这样呢？因为它再次提供了对物理资源的抽象。
and the abstractions are much easier to use on the applications than the application using
并且在应用程序上使用抽象比直接使用应用程序要容易得多。
directly the hardware, right? And one of the way it makes it easier to use, the operating
是的，直接操作硬件，对吗？而且其中一种使其更易于使用的方式是操作系统。
system makes easier for the application to use is removing limitations, right? So for
系统的作用是简化应用程序的使用，是通过消除限制来实现的，对吗？所以对于...
instance, it provides you the illusion to you being the application, the illusion that
它给你提供了一种错觉，让你觉得自己是这个应用程序，一种让你觉得自己是这个应用程序的错觉。
you are the only one, the application is the only one using that machine. It provides the
你是唯一的，这个应用是唯一一个使用那台机器的。它提供了
illusion that the memory is like infinite, there are no limits, right? It provides a
幻觉是记忆无限的感觉，没有限制，对吗？它提供了
illusion, you know, you have files and data is stored in files. You have users, you have
幻觉，你知道，你有文件和数据存储在文件中。你有用户，你有
messages. So it's a much higher level of abstraction than operating just on bits, right? And the
是的，消息传递是比仅仅操作位更高层次的抽象，对吗？而且
main way the operating system provides abstracts these resources, hardware resources to the
主要的方式是操作系统将这些资源进行抽象化，将硬件资源提供给应用程序。
application is through the process. The process is execution environment in which the applications
应用程序正在进行中。该过程是应用程序执行的环境。
run and the process consists of threads. This is basically the concept, the unit of execution.
运行和进程由线程组成。这基本上是执行的概念，执行的单位。
It's an address space. This is a unit kind of allocates, allocation, right? Allocate
这是一个地址空间。这是一种分配、分配的单位，对吗？分配
the resources and you allocate addresses, memory, and you have access to files and sockets
资源和您分配地址、内存，并且您可以访问文件和套接字。
to communicate over network, right? So the process encapsulate and provides all this
是的，用于在网络上进行通信。因此，该过程封装并提供所有这些功能。
abstraction to the application. So the application only need to understand about how to operate
抽象化对应用程序来说非常重要。因此，应用程序只需要了解如何操作即可。
on threads and address space, how to read, write files, how to communicate over a sockets
关于线程和地址空间，如何读取、写入文件，以及如何通过套接字进行通信。
to communicate over network, right? So that's it much easier. And how does application take
与网络通信，对吗？这样就容易多了。那么应用程序如何进行接收呢？
advantage? You write the code and you compile the code and your code is not only the code
优势？你编写代码，编译代码，而且你的代码不仅仅是代码。
you are writing, but it's going to use also libraries and a bunch of system libraries,
你正在编写代码，但它将使用一些库和一系列系统库。
which are coming with any operating system, right? So again, to summarize the application
是指那些随附任何操作系统的应用程序，对吗？所以，再次总结一下这个应用程序。
view of machine is that of the process. Each application program runs in its own process
机器的视角是过程的视角。每个应用程序在自己的进程中运行。
and this process provides this much higher level, much nicer interfaces than the raw
而这个过程提供了比原始界面更高级、更好的界面。
hardware. Okay? So it's again, here you can see is like I mentioned, you have the program,
硬件。好吗？所以，再次说一下，你可以看到这里就像我提到的那样，你有程序，
the code you write, which is going to use some calls to the system libraries, which
你编写的代码将使用一些对系统库的调用。
are going basically to implement this API for this abstraction, API, it's application
我们基本上要为这个抽象实现这个API，API是应用程序。
programming interfaces to manipulate these abstractions. And then you take care of this,
编写用于操作这些抽象的编程接口。然后你负责处理这个。
you compile it, you get the executable code and that you run it on your machine. Okay?
你编译它，得到可执行代码，然后在你的机器上运行它。好吗？
So let me stop here and let's see, there is a question. Oh, what OS do you like the best?
让我在这里停下来，我们来看看，有一个问题。哦，你最喜欢哪个操作系统？
Well, I think that's a good question. I think, look, you know, it's like you, I'm not going
好的，我认为这是一个好问题。我认为，你知道的，就像你一样，我不会
to surprise you here. I think that our two systems which are quite good, it's and I'm
让你惊讶的是，我认为我们的两个系统都相当不错，它们是这样的，而我也是这样的。
using them, it's Linux and Mac OS. And you know, Mac OS, we are going to talk about that.
使用它们的话，就是Linux和Mac OS。而且你知道，Mac OS，我们要谈谈它。
It's actually built also of the Unix BSD, which originated from Berkeley. So, okay.
它实际上也是基于Unix BSD构建的，而Unix BSD起源于伯克利。所以，好的。
So please ask questions. I am, and sorry, you know, again, it's I've never used webinar.
所以请问问题。我是的，抱歉，你知道的，再次说，我从来没有使用过网络研讨会。
We are using it because it's more scalable, but it's less interactive. And yeah, so, but
我们使用它是因为它更具可扩展性，但交互性较差。嗯，所以，但是
we promise to improve on using these tools. So, excellent. Again, just to summarize, and
我们承诺在使用这些工具上进行改进。所以，非常好。再次总结一下，然后
I'm going to repeat a lot of things, you know, a lot of over and over again. So hopefully
我会重复很多事情，你知道的，很多次重复。所以希望
I'm not going to bore you, but you know, there are actually not a lot of big concepts you
我不会让你感到无聊，但是你知道，实际上并没有很多大的概念。
are going to learn in this class, but the concepts are quite difficult and intricate
你将在这堂课上学习，但是概念相当困难和复杂。
it. And also because they need to, they are going to inter-operate and interact with each
它。而且因为他们需要，他们将相互操作和互动。
other. But just to summarize a process consists of an address space, one or more thread, and
其他。但是简单来说，一个进程由一个地址空间、一个或多个线程和其他组件组成。
this is the controls execution in that address space and a bunch of other resources like
这是在该地址空间中的控制执行以及一堆其他资源，比如...
files, sockets, and things like that. Okay. This is activity monitor. If you go, if you
文件、套接字和类似的东西。好的。这是活动监视器。如果你去，如果你
have a Mac, if you go on here, you can look and you can see all these processes and you
有一台Mac电脑，如果你在这里上网，你可以查看并且可以看到所有这些进程和你
can see actually the processes. It tells you also, I think the column probably, I'm not
能够实际看到这些过程。它还告诉你，我想可能是柱子，我不太确定。
sure you see my mouse, but there is a column here called threads, right? So this is your
当然，你能看到我的鼠标，但这里有一个叫做"threads"的列，对吗？所以这是你的。
unit of execution. So basically for Chrome here, you have 22 threads. So 22 activities
执行单元。所以基本上对于Chrome来说，你有22个线程。所以有22个活动。
which are running concurrently in the same process. Okay. So that's one. Again, we abstracting
同时在同一个进程中运行的是哪些？好的。那就是一个。再次，我们正在抽象化。
away hardware resources to the applications. It's one of the main, main things that the
应用程序占用硬件资源。这是其中一个主要的、主要的事情。
application is that the operating system is doing. The main capabilities. Now let's, we
应用程序是操作系统正在执行的任务。主要功能。现在让我们，我们
are going to look for other, we are going to go over the other capabilities that the
我们要去寻找其他的，我们要去了解其他的能力。
operating system provides and to illustrate the need for the next one. Now assume that
操作系统提供并且说明了对下一个操作系统的需求。现在假设
you are going to have not only one program, but two programs, two applications running
你将不仅拥有一个程序，而是两个程序，两个应用程序在运行。
on your machine. And you know that every actually today, almost every computer your laptop,
在你的机器上。而且你知道，实际上今天几乎每台电脑都是你的笔记本电脑，
your phone allows you to run multiple applications, which means multiple processes at the same
你的手机可以运行多个应用程序，这意味着可以同时运行多个进程。
time. Right? And this now the point is that it's again, it's like one of the abstractions
时间。对吗？现在的关键是，它又是一个抽象的东西，就像其中一个抽象一样。
remember that I mentioned that the operating system provides to the application is that
记得我提到过操作系统提供给应用程序的是什么。
provides the illusion of a dedicated machine. Right? But now how you are going to do it
提供了一个专用机器的幻觉。对吗？但是现在你打算如何做到这一点呢？
when you are going to have multiple applications running at the same time, because they are
当您要同时运行多个应用程序时，因为它们是
going to run on the same hardware. And here is where it comes this kind of the other way
将在相同的硬件上运行。这就是它采取这种另一种方式的地方。
you can look at the operating system as a referee. Because the only way you can provide
你可以把操作系统看作是一名裁判。因为它是唯一能够提供公平和有序环境的方式。
the illusion of two applications and each of them they have their own virtual machine,
两个应用程序的幻觉，每个应用程序都有自己的虚拟机。
so to speak, is to protect one of each other, to isolate one of each other. Right? That's
所谓保护彼此，就是相互保护，相互隔离。对吗？
the only way. And here it's just let's go in a little bit more details to illustrate
唯一的方法。这里我们只是稍微详细地说明一下。
the need for that. Now, let's start with a processor. So you have only one processor
对此的需求。现在，让我们从处理器开始。所以你只有一个处理器。
and you have two applications and you have to run on the same processor. At a given time,
你有两个应用程序，需要在同一处理器上运行。在给定的时间，
you can run on the processor only one application. So to give the illusion that both of them
你只能在处理器上运行一个应用程序。所以为了给人一种两者都在运行的错觉，
are going to run, you know, they have their own machine, so to speak. The way you do it
他们打算跑步，你知道，他们有自己的机器，可以这么说。你要做的方式是这样的。
is that you are going to divide the processor time in slots or slices. And each slice you
将处理器时间分割成时间片或切片。每个时间片你都会
have a different application running. The slices are, you know, a few milliseconds.
有一个不同的应用程序正在运行。这些切片，你知道的，只有几毫秒。
One millisecond, 10 milliseconds, something like that. Right? So in this particular example,
一毫秒，十毫秒，差不多是这样。对吗？所以在这个特定的例子中，
you have the brown application, right, running. And if you can see here, the processor accesses
你有布朗大学的申请表，对吧，正在运行。如果你能看到这里，处理器正在访问。
memory, which is allocated to the brown process, process one, and it reads the code and executes
内存分配给了进程一，也就是棕色进程，它读取代码并执行。
that code. So is there a for running program one. Right? But now, next, you will also have
那段代码。所以有一个用于运行程序的循环，对吗？但是现在，接下来，你还会有什么？
program two. So for program two, in memory, you also have some piece of, you also have
程序二。所以对于程序二，在内存中，你也有一些片段，你也有
some piece of memory which is allocated to process two. Right? And at some point, right,
一些分配给进程二的内存块，对吗？然后，在某个时刻，对吗？
you run, and at some point now, I said after a little bit of time, you allocate to program
你在跑步，然后在某个时刻，现在我说，在一段时间后，你分配时间来编程。
one to run. Now you are going to switch to program two. Right? And you are going to run.
一个要运行。现在你要切换到程序二。对吗？然后你要运行。
And by doing so and switching at a very high frequency, you give the illusion to each of
并通过这样做并以非常高的频率切换，你给每个人一种错觉
these applications that it's using the computer alone. Right?
这些应用程序是独自使用电脑的，对吗？
Now, the problem here, if you can see, for instance, if you look at the memory, you're
现在，这里的问题是，如果你能看到的话，比如说，如果你看一下内存，你会发现
having the same memory, physical memory, you have the data from multiple applications,
拥有相同的内存，物理内存，你可以获取来自多个应用程序的数据。
and they have to read and write the data. Right? And certainly, you do not want, say
他们必须阅读和写入数据。对吗？当然，你不希望，比如说
in this case, a program two or process two to read or even more to write the data in
在这种情况下，一个程序或者进程可以读取甚至写入多个数据。
process one, of process one. Right? You also don't want any process two or for that matter
第一步，关于第一步。对吗？你也不想要任何第二步或者其他的步骤。
of fact, any process to write, to modify the operating system memory. Right? Right?
事实上，任何编写、修改操作系统内存的过程。对吗？对吗？
because then the operating system may crash, right?
因为那样的话操作系统可能会崩溃，对吗？
If you let out an application,
如果你提交了一份申请，
modify the operating system in memory, right?
修改操作系统的内存中，对吗？
And also you need to be careful with the storage, right?
而且你需要注意存储，对吗？
You shouldn't allow one program of one user
你不应该允许一个用户的一个程序。
to modify the data of another users,
修改其他用户的数据。
especially if that data is private or read it, okay?
尤其是如果这些数据是私密的或者阅读它，好吗？
So this is what we mean now you need to,
这就是我们现在的意思，你需要...
you protect, protection.
你保护，保护。
So you need to protect one application,
所以你需要保护一个应用程序，
one process from another.
一个过程从另一个过程中产生。
You need to protect one process from the operating system
你需要保护一个进程免受操作系统的影响。
and protect the operating system from the process, right?
并保护操作系统免受进程的影响，对吗？
So when an application on a program tries to
因此，当程序中的一个应用程序尝试
execute some of these actions, which are precluded,
执行一些被排除的行动。
like accessing the data of, or the memory,
喜欢访问数据或内存的方式，
which belongs to another process
属于另一个进程
or accessing the memory belongs to the operating system.
或者访问属于操作系统的内存。
The operating system, one way is going to deal with this
操作系统有一种方法来处理这个问题。
offending application is crashing, crashing the processes,
冒犯的应用程序崩溃了，导致进程崩溃，
segmentation fault, okay?
分段错误，好吗？
But it's again, the main point here is that
但是，这里的主要问题是
in order to create this illusion of,
为了营造这种幻觉，
to a process that they are using the machine alone,
他们正在使用这台机器进行一个独立的过程。
you need to isolate and to protect processes
你需要隔离和保护进程。
from each other.
彼此之间。
Also in order to make sure that the operating system itself
也为了确保操作系统本身
is not crashes as a result of processes,
不会因为进程而崩溃。
modifying operating system data,
修改操作系统数据。
then you need also to,
然后你也需要，
we need also to isolate the operating system itself
我们还需要隔离操作系统本身。
from the processes.
从这些过程中。
So let's see.
那么让我们来看看。
Okay, I was looking at the question,
好的，我正在看这个问题，
why is a good time for learning OS right now?
为什么现在是学习操作系统的好时机？
It's again, we are going stick around until,
再次来了，我们会一直待下去，直到……
you know, for the next half an hour or so.
你知道，接下来大约半个小时。
Okay, so now the last way we can look at the
好的，现在我们可以看一下最后一种方式
operating system is like a glue, right?
操作系统就像一种胶水，对吗？
So why is that?
那为什么呢？
It's again, it's like, it's very logic, right?
这又是，就像，这非常合乎逻辑，对吗？
It's logical.
这是合乎逻辑的。
First, you need to abstract away the hardware
首先，你需要将硬件抽象化。
to make it much easier for the application developers
为了让应用开发者更容易
to write applications.
编写应用程序。
Second, you need to provide protection, isolations,
其次，您需要提供保护、隔离措施，
because typically you are going to have multiple
因为通常情况下，你会有多个
applications, multiple processes sharing the same hardware.
应用程序，多个进程共享相同的硬件。
And the final part is that these applications
而最后一部分是这些应用程序
or some applications are communicating with each other.
或者一些应用程序正在相互通信。
So you need to provide some kind of glue between them.
所以你需要提供一种粘合剂将它们连接起来。
You provide some common services.
你提供一些常见的服务。
And this is coming in the form of networking or storage,
这是以网络或存储的形式呈现的。
right? You can, application can communicate through files.
对吗？你可以，应用程序可以通过文件进行通信。
One application writing a file,
一个应用程序正在写入一个文件，
another application reads from a file.
另一个应用程序从文件中读取。
And obviously this also comes with authorization
而且显然这也需要授权。
and things like that.
等等之类的东西。
But this is when you can think about the operating system
但是这是你可以考虑操作系统的时候
as a glue, right?
作为胶水，对吗？
And they need to provide the communications,
他们需要提供通讯设备。
enable you the ability to share the resources.
使您能够共享资源。
And again, the operating system is doing that
再次，操作系统正在执行这个任务。
by providing these common services,
通过提供这些常见的服务，
file systems, networking, and so forth.
文件系统、网络等等。
Okay?
好的。
So I'm going to stop here.
所以我要在这里停下来。
Are there any questions?
有没有任何问题？
So one question is what are the methods
所以一个问题是什么方法
that allow different processes to talk with each other?
允许不同进程之间进行通信的方法是什么？
I know with socket communication, it's a valid method.
我知道使用套接字通信是一种有效的方法。
So there are a few of them
所以有几个他们。
and we are going to learn about them.
我们将要学习关于它们的知识。
Yeah, one is socket communication.
是的，其中一个是套接字通信。
So it's like networking, right?
所以这就像是建立人际关系，对吗？
You can communicate with each other, two processes,
你们可以互相交流，两个进程。
whether they are on the same machine
他们是否在同一台机器上
or different machines through sockets,
或者通过套接字连接到不同的机器，
through a network interface.
通过网络接口。
Okay?
好的？
The processes which are on the same machine,
这些在同一台机器上运行的进程，
they can also communicate through shared memory.
他们还可以通过共享内存进行通信。
You can also have the ability
你也可以拥有这个能力。
to communicate through shared memory.
通过共享内存进行通信。
And also, like I mentioned earlier,
而且，正如我之前提到的，
you can communicate through storage.
你可以通过存储进行通信。
An application can write a piece of data
一个应用程序可以写入一段数据。
on the local file system,
在本地文件系统上，
or even for a global file system,
或者甚至是用于全球文件系统，
and others application can read.
其他应用程序也可以阅读。
Okay?
好的。
Is a processor just what we call a CPU?
处理器就是我们所说的中央处理器（CPU）吗？
Yes, for most cases, these are interchangeable.
是的，对大多数情况来说，它们是可以互换的。
Although we are also going to call processor
虽然我们也会称之为处理器
like specialized hardware, specialized processors.
像专用硬件、专用处理器一样。
So processor is a little bit broader,
所以处理器的范围稍微广泛一些，
but unless otherwise specified, they are equivalent.
但是除非另有规定，否则它们是等效的。
Will ARM replace x86 in consumer space soon?
ARM is already making significant inroads in the consumer space and has the potential to replace x86 architecture in the future.
Well, it's clear that ARM has a lot of momentum right now.
嗯，很明显，ARM目前势头很强劲。
One example, it's obviously it's M1 from Apple.
一个例子，显然是苹果的M1。
And you see that become more and more powerful,
而且你会看到它变得越来越强大，
but there are also ARM starts to be deployed in data centers.
但是现在也开始在数据中心中部署ARM处理器。
Actually, there is one new instance
实际上，有一个新的实例。
which from Amazon called Graviton.
其中来自亚马逊的产品名为Graviton。
And this is around ARM processor.
这是关于ARM处理器的内容。
And it's quite fast.
而且它非常快速。
It's actually has very good performance and it's cheaper.
它实际上性能非常好，而且价格更便宜。
Now we'll see, right?
现在我们就看看，对吧？
Because you know what Intel is going to do,
因为你知道Intel将要做什么，
clearly they announced a bunch of initiatives, but yes.
显然他们宣布了一系列的举措，但是是的。
ARM, it's has a lot of momentum at this point.
ARM在目前有很大的势头。
Okay.
Sure, I can help you with that. Please go ahead and provide me with the text you would like me to translate.
Let me go here.
让我去这里。
Yeah, there is something about virtualization.
是的，虚拟化确实有一些特点。
There is something about,
有一件事情，
there are a few more questions here.
这里还有几个问题。
Let me answer them.
让我来回答它们。
It's one question on the chat.
这是一个聊天中的问题。
By the way, please try to ask question for on Q&A.
顺便说一下，请尝试在问答环节提出问题。
So I have one source I can read them from.
所以我有一个可以从中阅读它们的来源。
So yeah, there are a few more questions here.
嗯，是的，这里还有几个问题。
Yeah, there are some comments about VMware,
是的，有一些关于VMware的评论。
about virtualization.
关于虚拟化。
Yes, we are going to talk about virtualization
是的，我们将要讨论虚拟化。
even a little bit during this lecture.
在这堂讲座中，即使只有一点点也可以。
But yes, virtualization is a way to provide the illusion
但是，是的，虚拟化是一种提供幻觉的方式。
to every process, to every application
对于每个进程，对于每个应用程序
that they are using alone the machine.
他们正在独自使用这台机器。
There is another question about RISC-V.
关于RISC-V还有一个问题。
This obviously was done at Berkeley.
这显然是在伯克利完成的。
I think RISC-V has a great future.
我认为RISC-V有着很好的前景。
And for those of you who don't know,
对于那些不知道的人，
RISC-V is an open instruction set architecture,
RISC-V是一种开放的指令集架构，
which means that you don't need to pay any license to use it
这意味着您使用它时不需要支付任何许可费用。
to build processors around it.
围绕它来构建处理器。
In contrast ARM, for ARM you need to pay license
与ARM相比，对于ARM，您需要支付许可费用。
in order to use and to provide the ARM instruction set.
为了使用和提供ARM指令集。
But RISC-V now it's targeting Internet of Things
但是RISC-V现在的目标是物联网。
or mobile devices, very low power.
或移动设备，功耗非常低。
This is how they started, but this is the way ARM started.
这是他们的起点，但这就是ARM的起点。
So you'll see maybe RISC, there is a chance
所以你可能会看到RISC，有机会的话。
they are going to follow the trajectory of ARM
他们将会追随ARM的轨迹。
and it can become for ARM what ARM is for Intel, right?
是的，它可以成为对于ARM来说，就像ARM对于英特尔一样的存在，对吗？
But it's okay, it's obvious.
但没关系，这是显而易见的。
This is in the future, but obviously it has a lot of promise.
这是在未来，但显然有很多潜力。
Okay, I'm going to go back now to the lecture slides.
好的，我现在要回去看讲义幻灯片了。
Oops, okay.
抱歉，好的。
So it's again, this is give examples
所以，这是再次给出例子。
about some of the services which are provided
关于一些提供的服务
by the operating system, we didn't discuss so far.
关于操作系统，我们到目前为止还没有讨论过。
And some of the management services
和一些管理服务
and that the operating system provides
并且操作系统提供了什么。
and maybe you do not think right away to them.
也许你并不立刻想到他们。
It's like power management, right?
这就像是电源管理，对吗？
Well, especially for mobile devices,
好的，尤其是对于移动设备来说，
you need to manage the power and across the application,
你需要管理电源和应用程序之间的连接。
you have a application which use a disproportionate amount
你有一个应用程序使用了不成比例的数量。
of battery, maybe you want to isolate
电池没电了，也许你想要隔离一下。
to protect other application from that.
保护其他应用程序免受此影响。
And of course you need to manage the network,
当然，你还需要管理网络，
you need to manage almost every shared resource, right?
你需要管理几乎所有的共享资源，对吗？
When I mean share, I refer share by multiple applications.
当我说分享时，我指的是通过多个应用程序进行分享。
Okay, so in summary, it's again repeating, right?
好的，所以总结一下，又是在重复，对吗？
There are three things an operating system is doing.
操作系统正在进行三件事情。
One is providing a clean, easy to use abstractions
一个是提供一个干净、易于使用的抽象化界面。
of the physical resources to the application,
将物理资源分配给应用程序，
make it much easier for application developers
让应用开发者更容易。
to develop this application.
开发这个应用程序。
And this piece like you can think about this,
这个片子就像你可以思考一下，
like is like you lose your list.
喜欢就像你失去了清单。
Then which follows from providing clean abstractions,
从提供清晰的抽象中得出的结论是什么？
you can think about operating system as a referee.
你可以把操作系统看作是一名裁判。
And in this case, the operating system provides protection
而在这种情况下，操作系统提供保护。
and isolations of shared resources
和共享资源的隔离
across for multiple applications, right?
是的，可以用于多个应用。
We share those resources, okay?
我们共享这些资源，好吗？
And the final is that it's a glue
最后的结果是它是一种胶水。
that operating system provides common services
该操作系统提供常见的服务。
and in particularly also enables this application
并且特别是还使得这个应用程序能够实现
to communicate to each other, right?
是的，互相沟通，对吗？
So now let's talk a little bit more
所以现在让我们再多聊一点吧。
about CS162 in general,
关于CS162的总体情况，
and then talk a little bit about why now
然后稍微谈一下为什么现在。
and why it's exciting and challenging.
为什么这令人兴奋和具有挑战性。
So why take CS162?
那为什么要选修CS162呢？
It's again, because some of you will actually design
这又是因为你们中的一些人实际上会设计。
and build operating system or components of them,
并构建操作系统或其组件。
like file systems, right?
像文件系统一样，对吗？
You go to Google, you may work on Android, for instance.
你去Google，你可以在Android上工作，例如。
You go to Apple, you may, or Microsoft,
你可以去苹果公司，或者微软公司。
you may work on their operating systems.
你可以在他们的操作系统上工作。
Or if you are to any company,
或者如果你对任何公司感兴趣的话，
which depend running its software on Linux,
依赖于在Linux上运行其软件的
you may work on Linux to provide new capabilities
你可以在Linux上工作，提供新的功能。
for the applications that are important for your company.
对于对您公司重要的应用程序。
But many of you are going to build software
但是你们中的许多人将要开发软件。
which run on top of the operating systems.
运行在操作系统之上的。
And to build better software,
为了构建更好的软件，
you need to understand how the operating system was working.
你需要了解操作系统是如何工作的。
You need to understand the concepts, right?
你需要理解这些概念，对吗？
So that's what it is.
这就是它的原因。
So next time I'm going to talk about
下次我要谈论的是什么？
what makes operating system exciting and challenging.
什么使操作系统变得令人兴奋和具有挑战性。
And let me check again for the questions.
让我再次检查一下问题。
How can application interact with these common services?
应用程序如何与这些常见服务进行交互？
Through the API, application programming interfaces.
通过API，应用程序编程接口。
I mentioned a little bit in passing earlier on.
我之前只是顺便提到了一点。
And these are exposed by system libraries, right?
是的，这些是由系统库暴露出来的，对吗？
For instance, if you want to access a file,
例如，如果你想要访问一个文件，
you are going to have an API to access that file.
你将拥有一个API来访问那个文件。
Read, write, seek.
读，写，探索。
The same for communication, sending and receiving data.
通信、发送和接收数据也是一样的。
You are going to have another API.
你将会有另一个API。
And this is exposed by the system libraries
这是由系统库暴露出来的。
and implement it.
并且实施它。
Well, why does searching for files
好的，为什么要搜索文件呢？
on Windows File Explorer feel super slow?
在Windows文件资源管理器上感觉非常慢吗？
Unfortunately, I don't know.
很遗憾，我不知道。
I have no answer to that question,
我对那个问题没有答案。
but if you get the answer,
但是如果你得到答案，
I'll be interested in the answer.
我对答案很感兴趣。
Okay, so in short,
好的，简而言之，
what makes the system, the operating system,
什么构成了系统，操作系统，
now extremely exciting
现在非常令人兴奋。
is because there are many things happening.
是因为有很多事情正在发生。
In the next few slides,
在接下来的几张幻灯片中，
I'm going to tell you what happens.
我要告诉你发生了什么事情。
And these things actually makes operating systems,
这些东西实际上构成了操作系统。
addressing the operating system problems more difficult
解决操作系统问题更加困难。
and hopefully more rewarding once you solve the problems.
并且一旦你解决了问题，希望会更加有回报。
So as you probably know, and you heard that,
所以你可能知道，你听说过，
I'm sure everyone heard that many times,
我相信每个人都听过很多次，
for the most than, more than 50 years,
在过去的50多年中，
all our industry, hardware industry, software industry,
我们所有的行业，硬件行业，软件行业，
and large part was really driven by the morsel.
而且很大一部分实际上是由这个细小的部分推动的。
Machines are harder becoming more and more powerful,
机器变得越来越强大。
very fast.
非常快。
So according to Gordon Moore,
据戈登·摩尔所说，
who was a co-founder of Intel,
英特尔的联合创始人是谁？
in '65 he predicted that the transistor density
在1965年，他预测晶体管密度会增加。
of semiconductor chips will double roughly every two years.
半导体芯片的数量大约每两年翻一番。
That's a morsel, right?
那是一小口，对吗？
And you have this plus here and you see a line,
而且你在这里有一个加号，然后你会看到一条线，
but you see a line on the X axis is the time,
但是你看到X轴上的一条线代表的是时间，
on the Y axis it's the performance
在Y轴上是性能。
or the number of transistors.
或者晶体管的数量。
And you have a line, why?
你有什么问题吗？
Because the Y axis is in log scale.
因为Y轴是对数刻度。
Now, Moore's law says every,
现在，摩尔定律说每
the transistor density doubles roughly every two years.
晶体管密度大约每两年翻一番。
So in the same, on the same area,
在同一个地方
you can cram twice as many transistors.
你可以将晶体管数量增加一倍。
And this leads to the performance of the processor,
这导致了处理器的性能。
doubling roughly every 18 months.
每18个月翻一番左右。
Why discrepancy?
为什么不一致？
The discrepancy is because since the transistors
差异是因为自从晶体管
are becoming closer to each other,
彼此越来越接近，
the latency between transistors to communicate
晶体管之间的延迟以进行通信
between transistors decreases.
晶体管之间的距离减小了。
And therefore you have double reasons.
所以你有双重理由。
You know, you have, there are these compounds.
你知道，你有，有这些化合物。
To increasing the transistor density.
为了增加晶体管密度。
And therefore the performance increases a little bit faster
所以性能提升速度稍微快一点。
or used to increase a little bit faster.
或者用来稍微增加一点速度。
Okay?
好的。
The challenge is that the Moore's law ended.
挑战在于摩尔定律的终结。
Okay?
好的。
This again, it shows here the performance
这又是一次，这里显示了表现。
and versus time, the performance of a single core
和时间的对比，单个核心的性能
of a processor.
处理器的一部分。
And between 1985 and 2002 or 2003,
1985年至2002年或2003年之间，
this was where you see here with green,
这是你在这里看到的绿色地方。
this is the golden age, so to speak.
这是所谓的黄金时代。
Because in this period, performance,
因为在这个时期，表现，
increased, doubled every 18 months
每18个月增加一倍。
or increased 52% every year.
或者每年增长52%。
And the problem right now is that this performance per core
目前的问题是每个核心的性能。
increases just a few percent every year.
每年只增长几个百分点。
Okay?
好的？
So that's it.
就是这样了。
Okay?
好的？
So this is a big problem.
这是一个大问题。
And why is this a big problem?
为什么这是一个大问题呢？
Because at the time when the capabilities of a single core
因为在单个核心的能力达到极限的时候
basically are no longer increasing.
基本上不再增加。
The demands of the new applications
新应用的需求
are increasing faster than ever.
正在以前所未有的速度增长。
So here it's a plot, open AI plot.
这是一个情节，开放AI的情节。
Many of you maybe may have seen it.
你们中的许多人可能已经看过了。
And it shows compute requirements
并且显示了计算要求。
to train the state of the art models.
训练最先进的模型。
This is plot was going back to 2012, was published in 2019.
这个情节是回溯到2012年，于2019年出版。
Again, it's a log scale.
再次强调，这是一个对数刻度。
And if you look here, this growth is absolutely astounding.
而且，如果你看这里，这个增长绝对令人惊讶。
The requirements, compute requirements
需求，计算需求
grew 35 times every 18 months.
每18个月增长了35倍。
And I added here another data point for 2020.
我在这里添加了2020年的另一个数据点。
A new model was released, if you remember,
一款新型号已经发布了，如果你还记得的话，
a little more than one year ago, GPT-C.
一年多前，GPT-C。
3 from OpenAI made a lot of waves.
3来自OpenAI引起了很大的轰动。
It has 175 million parameters.
它有1.75亿个参数。
And it's again, it fills a curve.
而且，它又填满了一个曲线。
And this again, is not only esoteric models.
而且，这并不仅限于深奥的模型。
You have models like GPT-3 is actually language model,
你们有像GPT-3这样的模型，实际上是语言模型。
video model, pattern recognition,
视频模型，模式识别。
and things like that.
等等之类的东西。
And now here is a Moore's law.
现在，这里是摩尔定律。
Actually, the Moore's law even forget that it ended.
实际上，摩尔定律甚至忘记了它已经结束了。
Even if it weren't ended, we would be in a big trouble.
即使它没有结束，我们也会陷入大麻烦中。
But of course, it ended.
但是当然，它结束了。
And this is actually how the Moore's law looked like.
这实际上就是摩尔定律的样子。
So you see the gap.
所以你看到了这个差距。
This is huge.
这是巨大的。
And this is exponential.
这是指数级的增长
It's again, you have a log scale here.
这里又是一个对数刻度。
And the gap increases exponentially every year
而且这个差距每年呈指数增长。
or every day if you want.
或者每天，如果你愿意的话。
OK?
好的？
So now what do you do about it?
那么现在你打算怎么处理呢？
Of course, you heard about specialized processors.
当然，你听说过专用处理器。
You have GPUs like Nvidia GPUs.
你有像Nvidia GPU这样的GPU。
A100 is the latest one.
A100是最新的。
TPUs from TensorFlow processor units, from Google.
来自谷歌的TensorFlow处理器单元（TPUs）。
Cerebras, this is a company building huge chips,
Cerebras，这是一家正在制造巨型芯片的公司，
very powerful.
非常强大。
And everyone else builds their own version of GPU.
而其他人都在构建自己的GPU版本。
Intel, Alchemist, Newer Announcement, AMD, Radion,
英特尔，炼金术士，新的公告，AMD，雷龙。
and so forth.
等等。
So the main idea here, obviously with this specialized hardware,
所以这里的主要思想显然是，通过这种专用硬件，
is that you are going to narrow the workloads you
你是要减少工作量吗？
want to support.
想要支持。
And because of that, you know more about that workload.
因此，你对那个工作量更了解。
So you can do more optimizations.
所以你可以进行更多的优化。
And you can be smarter in the way you design the chip.
你可以在设计芯片的方式上更加聪明。
You increase the parallelism and things like that.
你增加并行性和类似的东西。
So you can make it much faster for that workload
所以你可以让它处理那个工作负载更快速一些。
than a general proposed processor.
比一般提议的处理器更好。
But now you need to program these things as well.
但是现在你也需要编程这些东西。
You may need to share these things as well.
你可能也需要分享这些东西。
And they are going to be quite different from the CPUs.
而它们将与中央处理器（CPU）相当不同。
And who has to deal with that?
那个问题由谁来处理？
That's biggest stand if your operating system
这是你操作系统的最大支持。
has to deal with it.
必须处理它。
OK?
好的。
Now, the problem is that even with this specialized hardware,
现在的问题是，即使有了这种专用硬件，
they help.
他们帮忙。
Obviously, they are more powerful than a single core.
显然，它们比单核更强大。
But still, they don't close the gap.
但是，他们仍然没有弥合差距。
And here, it's the performance of the GPUs and of the TPUs
这里是GPU和TPU的性能表现。
on the same plot.
在同一地块上。
And there is a star here, basically,
这里有一颗星星，基本上，
saying we are assuming in order to make sense
我们假设是为了让事情有意义。
and to normalize, typically, in particular,
并且进行标准化，通常来说，特别是，
based on open AI data, the utilization of the hardware
基于Open AI的数据，硬件的利用率
by this state-of-the-art training algorithms
通过这些先进的训练算法
is like 33%.
是大约33%。
So when I show the performance of the GPUs and TPUs here,
那么当我在这里展示GPU和TPU的性能时，
I am factoring it for that utilization.
我正在为那个用途进行因式分解。
So that's a huge problem, right?
那是一个巨大的问题，对吗？
Even with the CPUs and GPUs.
即使有中央处理器（CPUs）和图形处理器（GPUs）。
And these memory demands are growing as fast, even faster.
而且这些内存需求正在以更快的速度增长。
So here, it's a log-log scale.
这里是一个对数-对数尺度。
Here is the number of parameters of these models.
这些模型的参数数量如下。
And this is from 2016.
这是来自2016年的。
And now, the last point is this Vodao.
现在，最后一个点是这个Vodao。
This is from China.
这是来自中国的。
And this is 1.75 trillion parameters.
这是1.75万亿个参数。
So it's 10 times larger than GPT-3.
所以它比GPT-3大10倍。
And I'm sure you are going to hear
我相信你会听到的。
about other announcement, even bigger models.
关于其他公告，甚至还有更大的型号。
So if you plot and if you look at this data,
那么，如果你绘制图表并查看这些数据，
it's again, it's again log scale,
这又是，这又是对数刻度。
although it may not look like.
虽然它可能看起来不像。
Since 2016, the size of this model
自2016年以来，这个模型的尺寸
increased 40 times every 18 months.
每18个月增长了40倍。
And if you look at the last three years, 340 times.
而且如果你看过去三年，共计340次。
This is phenomenal.
这太棒了。
During this time, the GPU memory, 1.7x every 18 months.
在这段时间内，GPU的内存每18个月增长1.7倍。
So it used to be, not a few years back, in 2017, '18,
那么，不是几年前的事了，在2017年、2018年，
you can fit the largest models on a single GPU.
你可以在单个GPU上容纳最大的模型。
Now, you need more than 1,000 GPUs
现在，你需要超过1,000个GPU。
just to store the parameters of the largest models.
只是为了存储最大模型的参数。
OK?
好的。
So let's see what are the other trends.
那么让我们看看其他的趋势是什么。
Now, let's move to storage capacity.
现在，让我们来谈谈存储容量。
Storage capacity is still growing,
存储容量仍在增长。
still growing exponentially.
仍在指数级增长。
And the one thing here, it used to be dominating the storage
而这里的一件事，它曾经主导着存储。
by hard disk drives.
通过硬盘驱动器。
No longer.
不再。
Now, you have more and more solid state devices.
现在，你有越来越多的固态设备。
And you can see here the capacity of a solid state drive
这里可以看到固态硬盘的容量。
started to exceed in 2015, '16.
开始在2015年和2016年超过。
So the biggest SSD drive exceeded
所以最大的固态硬盘超出了预期。
the capacity of the biggest, hardest drive around 2015
2015年左右最大、最硬的硬盘容量是多少？
to '16.
到'16年。
And today, if you are looking, the largest SSD,
而今天，如果你在寻找的话，最大的固态硬盘是
3.5 inch drive, is 100 terabytes.
3.5英寸硬盘，容量为100TB。
The largest SSD is 18 terabytes.
最大的固态硬盘容量为18TB
Now, you are going to pay dearly for this 100 terabyte SSD
现在，你将为这个100TB固态硬盘付出巨大的代价。
drive.
驾驶。
It costs 40K.
它的价格是40K。
It's 400 per terabytes.
每个太字节是400元。
While to get 18 terabytes, sorry, this
虽然要获得18TB，抱歉，这
is hardest drive.
是最困难的驱动器。
I'm sorry.
对不起。
I'm going to just correct this one.
我只是要纠正这一个。
OK?
好的。
So for that, you pay only $600, so you're $33 per terabytes.
所以为此，你只需支付600美元，即每TB 33美元。
Now, you can have more economical choices
现在，你可以有更经济实惠的选择。
when you look at the SSDs.
当你看着固态硬盘时。
Like, for instance, if you want 4 terabytes SSD,
比如，如果你想要4TB的固态硬盘，
it costs $95 per terabyte, still more expensive
每个1TB的价格是95美元，仍然比较贵。
than the hardest drives.
比最难的驱动器更耐用。
Despite of this, the SSDs are winning the war.
尽管如此，固态硬盘（SSD）正在赢得这场战争。
There is little question about that.
这毫无疑问。
And why?
为什么呢？
Because, yes, the hardest drive are cheaper,
因为，是的，最难的驱动器更便宜。
but they are much slower.
但是它们要慢得多。
Sometimes between 10x and 100x consumes much more power,
有时候，10倍到100倍之间的功耗会更高。
very important for data center and mobile devices or laptops.
非常重要的是数据中心和移动设备或笔记本电脑。
And they are less reliable.
而且它们不太可靠。
And these are some projections to drive home
这些是一些用来强调的投影。
that point on the left-hand side.
左侧的那个点。
It's about, you can see different technologies.
这是关于，你可以看到不同的技术。
It is projected up to 2030.
这是预计到2030年的。
And you can have here with dark blue, it's SSDs.
你可以选择这里的深蓝色，它是固态硬盘。
With light blue, it's flash.
用浅蓝色，它闪烁。
So this is USB, the storage in your camera,
这是USB，相机中的存储设备，
and things like that.
等等之类的东西。
And then the yellow, it's actually are tapes.
然后那个黄色的，实际上是磁带。
It's older technology.
这是较旧的技术。
Probably many of you have never seen a tape,
可能你们中的很多人从未见过磁带，
but they are very cheap.
但是它们非常便宜。
That's why.
这就是为什么。
And then, always, the dark orange--
然后，总是，深橙色--
well, with orange, it's actually hardest drives.
嗯，对于橙色来说，实际上是最难的驱动器。
Also, the same study anticipates that in 2026, actually,
同样的研究预测，实际上在2026年，
the SSDs will be cheaper per terabyte than hardest drives.
SSD的每TB价格将比硬盘更便宜。
And that's why probably you are going to see
而这也是为什么你可能会看到的原因
on the left-hand side a point in around 2025
在左侧大约2025年的一个点。
after which the market share of not only of the hardest drive,
之后，不仅是最难的驱动器的市场份额，
it's going to decrease.
会减少。
Networking, still growing very fast.
网络，仍然以非常快的速度增长。
Today, you can have 100-gabits connections
今天，你可以拥有100兆比特的连接速度。
to your machines in AWS.
将您的机器部署在AWS上。
Next will be probably 400-gabits per second.
下一个可能是每秒400个千兆位。
And there are other factors.
还有其他因素。
It's like, for instance, another important aspect
这是，例如，另一个重要的方面。
is the fact that it used to be early on,
这个事实是它过去曾经早期的一个原因，
you have very few huge computers because they
你们有很少的大型计算机，因为它们
are extremely expensive, tens of millions of dollars.
非常昂贵，数千万美元。
So in that case, you have a lot of people
那么在这种情况下，你有很多人。
using the same machine, right?
使用同一台机器，对吗？
Actually, in '60s, if I remember correctly, or '50s,
实际上，在60年代，如果我没记错的话，或者50年代，
when IBM started to build computers, Watson,
当IBM开始建造计算机时，沃森，
who was the founder of the IBM and the CEO,
IBM的创始人和首席执行官是谁？
was saying that he doesn't believe
他说他不相信。
that there is a need for more than five or six computers
需要超过五六台电脑。
in the entire United States.
在整个美国。
And of course, over time, the computers have proliferated,
当然，随着时间的推移，计算机数量不断增加，
become smaller and smaller.
越来越小。
And it used to be probably in 2000s,
而且它可能是在2000年代的时候，
at the end of the previous century,
上个世纪末，
you have one user, one computer.
你有一个用户，一个电脑。
And now you have one user with many, many computers.
现在你有一个用户拥有很多很多台电脑。
If you're in your car alone, you have 10 and 10 of CPUs, right?
如果你一个人在车里，你有10个和10个CPU，对吗？
So this change, and as you can imagine,
所以这个变化，正如你所能想象的，
this also is going to impact the way
这也将影响的方式。
you are going to design the operating systems.
你将要设计操作系统。
And there is another aspect here.
还有另一个方面。
There is an extreme range of timescales.
时间尺度有非常广泛的范围。
This is from Jeff Dean of Google,
这是来自Google的Jeff Dean。
very influential computer scientist,
非常有影响力的计算机科学家
built many of the distributed systems there.
在那里构建了许多分布式系统。
And if you look about from an application and the operating
如果你从一个应用程序和操作系统的角度来看的话，
system, you have to deal with a latency as low as lower
系统，你需要处理尽可能低的延迟。
than one second.
少于一秒钟。
This is L1 cache.
这是L1缓存。
This is a cache which is the first level cache which
这是一个缓存，是第一级缓存。
is on the chip, on chip.
在芯片上，就在芯片上。
And all the way, if you are going
一路上，如果你要去的话
to send a packet to communicate with someone in California
发送一个数据包与加利福尼亚的某人进行通信
to Netherlands, it's what?
去荷兰，是什么？
It's 150 milliseconds.
这是150毫秒。
So you need to handle a scale, a difference in scale,
所以你需要处理一个尺度，一个尺度的差异，
and range of what, eight order of magnitude, more, OK?
和范围是什么，八个数量级以上，对吗？
So basically, let me actually stop here
所以基本上，让我实际上在这里停下来。
and see what are the questions.
然后看看有哪些问题。
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
[侧面对话]
Why does industry Intel Apple say the Moore's Law is not
为什么英特尔和苹果公司都说摩尔定律不再适用？
over?
结束了吗？
So the Moore's Law, from that very definition of the Moore's
摩尔定律，从摩尔定律的定义来看，
Law, it is pretty much over.
法律，基本上已经结束了。
It's physical, right?
是身体的，对吗？
What they say is that--
他们说的是--
what this company is saying, it's fundamentally-- look,
这家公司所说的，从根本上说——看，
if the Moore's Law--
如果摩尔定律--
if you say that the Moore's Law is over,
如果你说摩尔定律结束了，
and I'm building chips, why would you build--
而我正在制造芯片，你为什么要制造——
why you would buy chips from me?
为什么你要从我这里购买薯片呢？
Because this means that the new chips
因为这意味着新芯片
will be the same like the old chips.
将会和旧的芯片一样。
No more power, right?
没有更多的电力了，对吗？
So there is a limit also of this, that I cannot say that
所以这也有一个限制，我不能说
the Moore's Law is over, because the Moore's Law is
摩尔定律已经结束了，因为摩尔定律已经达到了极限。
what the public associate with the performance, right?
公众与表演相关联的是什么，对吗？
So it's a limit of also marketing.
所以这也是市场营销的限制。
The Moore's Law is over, but the Moore's Law
摩尔定律已经结束，但摩尔定律
has a very precise definition.
有一个非常精确的定义。
And these companies, they talk to the public,
这些公司，他们与公众交流，
and the public doesn't know the precise definition.
而公众并不知道确切的定义。
Now, Moore's Law means fast.
现在，摩尔定律意味着快速。
Things become faster and faster.
事情变得越来越快。
Now, in truth, they use a lot of other techniques,
现在，实际上，他们使用了很多其他技术，
and we are going to talk about those in order
我们将按顺序讨论这些事项。
to improve the performance, right?
提高表现，对吗？
And this is very visible in your iPhone or in your Android phone.
这一点在你的iPhone或Android手机上非常明显。
And we'll talk a little bit about how they do it.
然后我们会稍微谈谈他们是如何做到的。
But that is not by improving necessarily
但这并不一定是通过改进来实现的。
the performance of a single core.
单核性能。
It's by adding GPUs, neural engines, adding more cores,
通过添加GPU、神经引擎和更多核心来实现。
things like that.
这样的事情。
OK?
好的。
We'll talk more about it.
我们会进一步讨论这个问题。
But good question.
但是好问题。
So there are programs like Spark and Mavic
所以有像Spark和Mavic这样的程序。
that allow us to use networks or computers to process
这允许我们使用网络或计算机进行处理。
a parallel workload.
一个并行工作负载。
But would it be feasible to create
但是创建这个是否可行呢？
some type of operating system of software
一种操作系统或软件类型
that could string together resources of multiple computers
可以将多台计算机的资源串联起来。
for personal consumer use?
个人消费使用？
I think-- so the question is, is a distributed operating system.
我认为--所以问题是，它是一个分布式操作系统。
I think that there is not a coherent operating system,
我认为目前没有一个连贯的操作系统。
but the elements of a operating system, distributed operating
但操作系统的要素，分布式操作系统
system, are already there.
系统已经存在。
Because one thing you can have, you can have--
因为有一件事情你可以拥有，你可以拥有--
you probably know about Kubernetes.
你可能了解Kubernetes。
Kubernetes provides resource orchestration,
Kubernetes 提供资源编排，
resource management over multiple machines,
多台机器上的资源管理
over a cluster.
在一个集群上。
So that's one.
那就是一个。
Then now, then you have distributed file systems,
然后现在，你有分布式文件系统。
like HDFS, or you have these block stores, like AWS S3.
像HDFS这样的，或者你有这些块存储，像AWS S3。
We'll talk more toward the end of the class.
我们会在课程结束前再多聊一些。
It's a good question.
这是一个好问题。
So probably you should expect that at some point
所以你应该预计在某个时候会发生这种情况
you are going to see these kind of pieces coming together
你将会看到这些部分开始组合在一起。
in a more coherent way in what you could call a distributed
以更连贯的方式，可以称之为分布式的方式。
operating system.
操作系统。
So fundamentally, it's again-- so why things are exciting?
所以从根本上说，为什么事情会令人兴奋呢？
Because they are challenging.
因为它们具有挑战性。
Why are things challenging?
为什么事情会具有挑战性？
Because they are complex.
因为它们很复杂。
And this complexity, it's growing fast.
而且这种复杂性正在迅速增长。
Why is complexity growing?
为什么复杂性在增加？
Because you have the demands of your new application
因为你有新应用的需求
are growing faster than ever.
正在以前所未有的速度增长。
Capabilities of the hardware are no longer
硬件的功能已不再是
growing like they used to be.
不再像过去那样快速增长。
So then you need to add to have--
那么你需要添加的是--
to innovate on the architecture.
创新建筑设计。
You have different specialized chips.
你有不同的专用芯片。
You need to distribute these applications.
你需要分发这些应用程序。
You need to parallelize the programs and many more.
你需要将程序并行化，还有很多其他的事情。
And I'll talk a little more about it.
然后我会再多谈一点关于它的事情。
So and then the applications themselves are more complicated.
所以，这些应用程序本身更加复杂。
The application consists of a variety of software modules.
该应用程序由多个软件模块组成。
And we'll talk more about that.
我们会更详细地讨论这个问题。
But remember, if you--
但是记住，如果你--
almost every application you are using today
几乎你今天使用的每个应用程序
is not running only on your machine.
不仅在你的机器上无法运行。
It has a back end.
它有一个后端。
Use Facebook.
使用Facebook。
A lot of things happen in the back end.
后台发生了很多事情。
Use Google or any other Google applications.
使用谷歌或任何其他谷歌应用程序。
80% is in the back end.
80%是在后端。
Twitter, everything almost, right?
Twitter, 几乎什么都有，对吧？
Netflix, name it, right?
是的，Netflix，没错吧？
And then it has to run on different hardware
然后它必须在不同的硬件上运行。
architectures.
建筑设计。
And because of the Moore's law has ended,
由于摩尔定律的终结，
you are going to have to see a proliferation.
你将会看到一种增加。
You are already seeing a proliferation
你已经看到了一种激增。
of hardware architectures.
硬件架构的研究领域。
Just to give you an example here,
只是给你举个例子，
and it's a personal example.
这是一个个人的例子。
When we started Spark and we started in 2009, so what,
当我们开始创办Spark时，是在2009年，那又怎样呢？
12 years ago, we are focusing only
12年前，我们只关注
for processing data which is in the memory efficiently.
用于高效处理存储在内存中的数据。
We are focusing only on CPUs, right?
我们只专注于CPU，对吗？
It's like we assume that the processing is
这就像我们假设处理是...
done by the general proposed processors, Intel.
由英特尔提出的通用处理器完成。
When we started Ray, which was--
当我们开始Ray的时候，这是-
that was happening like in 2016.
那是发生在2016年的事情。
So it's after only six, seven years.
所以只过了六七年。
We already have to take into account
我们已经必须考虑到
and to design it for heterogeneous hardware
并为异构硬件进行设计。
to handle GPUs at that time, now to handle GPUs and so forth.
在那个时候处理GPU，现在处理GPU等等。
So this is real.
是的，这是真的。
And obviously, this comes with additional complexity.
显然，这会带来额外的复杂性。
And of course, it's once you are over the network,
当然，这是在你连接到网络之后，
you are also exposed to attacks.
你也会受到攻击的威胁。
And this means that because the heterogeneity is increasing
这意味着由于异质性的增加
dramatically, that the operating system becomes
显著地，操作系统变得
even more important because it's much harder
更重要的是，因为它更加困难。
to abstract them away, right?
将它们抽象化，对吗？
Because if you don't abstract away,
因为如果你不进行抽象处理，
it's very hard to write applications.
写应用程序非常困难。
And the operating system is one of the key roles,
而操作系统是其中一个关键角色。
like we discussed, is to make that writing, developing
像我们讨论过的那样，目标是将那篇写作进一步发展。
application very easy, right?
申请非常简单，对吗？
So that's why its operating system are more challenging
所以这就是为什么它的操作系统更具挑战性。
and more needed than ever.
比以往任何时候都更加需要。
Now, we discussed and when we discussed about specialized hardware, I mentioned that it's
现在，我们讨论了一下，当我们讨论专用硬件时，我提到它是...
not only specialized hardware, how people try to go around the more slow or kind of,
不仅仅是专用硬件，人们还尝试绕过更慢或类似的问题。
so to speak, extend in terms of performance.
所谓的，就性能而言，扩展。
In other ways, having more and more cores, even for general proposed processors.
在其他方面，即使对于一般提议的处理器来说，拥有越来越多的核心也是有益的。
Like Intel Xeon Phi has a processor with 64 cores, AMD Epic, the same 64 cores, although
像英特尔骁龙Phi一样，它拥有一个拥有64个核心的处理器，AMD Epic也是一样的，拥有64个核心，尽管如此。
there are rumors that the new version will have 128 cores.
有传言称新版本将拥有128个核心。
And if you look at these processors, actually, they are damn complicated, right?
如果你看这些处理器，实际上，它们真的非常复杂，对吧？
This is how it looks like.
这是它的外观。
You have a bunch of cores, you have cache, you have some other components to manage memory.
你有一堆核心，你有缓存，你有其他组件来管理内存。
You have other components here down to also control the IO, input output, getting the
您在这里还有其他组件，用于控制输入输出（IO）。
data in and out of the processor and reading from the memory, which is not on the chip,
处理器内部的数据进出和从存储器中读取，存储器不在芯片上。
it's off the chip.
它不在芯片上。
And you have also in many systems, you have processor, you have some integrated graphics,
而且在许多系统中，你还有处理器，还有一些集成的图形处理器，
right?
对吗？
And this is a trend which, sorry, if you look under the hood, they are connected.
这是一个趋势，抱歉，如果你仔细观察，它们是相互关联的。
It's like a mini system in miniature, right?
是的，就像一个迷你版的系统一样，对吗？
In this case, you are going to have, this is a core, processor core, and now you are
在这种情况下，你将拥有一个核心，处理器核心，现在你正在使用它。
connected to different IO ports, memory, and many other things, right?
连接到不同的IO端口、内存和许多其他东西，对吗？
And this complexity just increasing.
而且这种复杂性还在不断增加。
So here down is like, it's what we are seeing here, it's another trend.
所以这里下面就像是，我们在这里看到的，是另一种趋势。
It's system on a chip, right?
是的，它是一款系统级芯片，对吗？
And when going back to that question, when Apple say, maybe say Moore's law is not done,
当回到那个问题时，当苹果说，也许说摩尔定律还没有完成时，
this is what they do and how they sustain the increasing performance, again, which is
这是他们所做的以及如何保持不断提高的表现，再次强调，这是他们的方式。
not necessarily related with the Moore's law.
不一定与摩尔定律相关。
It's putting more and more intelligence, more and more functionality on the same chip, right?
是的，它正在将越来越多的智能和功能集成在同一芯片上，对吗？
And here I will show, you have not only CPUs and if CPU have multiple cores, I mean, send
在这里，我将展示给你看，你不仅拥有CPU，而且如果CPU有多个核心，我是说，发送。
or eight between six and 10, but you have GPUs, right?
或者六到十之间的八个，但是你有GPU吗？
Integrated on the same chip.
集成在同一芯片上。
You have eight core GPUs, right?
你有八个核心的GPU，对吗？
Eight core CPUs.
八核心的中央处理器。
And in addition to that, you have neural engine, which is really focused on neural, to sort
而且，你还有神经引擎，它专注于神经网络的排序。
of supporting machine learning workloads, deep neural network workloads, right?
是的，支持机器学习工作负载和深度神经网络工作负载。
This is the things which are like, you know, your fingerprint sensor or recognizing, you
这些东西就像指纹传感器或识别器一样，你知道的。
know, as your face, using your face to unlock the phone, right?
是的，你可以使用你的脸来解锁手机。
Face recognition, right?
人脸识别，对吗？
So that's why, how you are going to get more performance.
所以这就是为什么，你打算如何提高性能。
The code is also very complicated.
这段代码也非常复杂。
It's growing in complexity and I don't have the numbers, more recent numbers, but here
它的复杂性正在增加，我没有最新的数据，但是
is a Vista, this one, you know, 15 years ago, code.
这是一个Vista，你知道的，15年前的代码。
It was what?
这是什么意思？
50 millions code, lines of code.
五千万行代码。
It's huge, huge complexity.
这是巨大的、极其复杂的。
And just to give you a sense, the NASA space shuttle, you know, you remember it was a space
而且只是为了让你有个概念，NASA的航天飞机，你知道的，你还记得它是一个航天飞机。
shuttle.
穿梭机。
It's no longer in service.
它已经停止服务了。
It has what?
它有什么？
I don't know.
我不知道。
One or two millions lines of code.
一到两百万行代码。
It's crazy.
太疯狂了。
And then it's again, like I mentioned several times, you have to scale everyone to, because
然后又是一样的，就像我之前多次提到的那样，你必须对每个人进行衡量，因为
you can no longer do these workloads on a single node, on a single machine, right?
你不能再在单个节点、单个机器上完成这些工作负载了，对吗？
Like I show you the data for machine learning workloads.
我给你展示机器学习工作负载的数据。
The same thing is for big data analytics, scientific computing.
同样的情况也适用于大数据分析和科学计算。
You have, so we have supercomputers, which are parallel computers or in this big computers
你有，所以我们有超级计算机，它们是并行计算机或者说是大型计算机。
since 80s to support this kind of workloads.
自80年代以来，支持这种工作量。
And then on top of that, everything is connected.
而且，除此之外，一切都是相互关联的。
This is the internet.
这是互联网。
Probably the most impressive artifact that humans have created, right?
可能是人类创造的最令人印象深刻的文物，对吧？
It's linked the entire world, right?
是的，它连接了整个世界，对吗？
And it's what?
这是什么？
You have 4.5 billions people connected to the internet.
你有45亿人连接到互联网。
This is what this plot shows, right?
这个图表显示的就是这个，对吗？
And this is what?
这是什么？
It happens only 25 years.
这只发生在25年内。
It's quite amazing.
真是太令人惊叹了。
And then the smartphone shipments exceeded the PC shipments, what I think in 2011.
然后智能手机的出货量超过了个人电脑的出货量，我认为是在2011年。
And today, right, today actually it turns out that you have close to 4 billion smartphones
今天，对吧，今天实际上发现你们拥有接近40亿部智能手机。
and 5 point something billions mobile phones, right?
是的，大约有50多亿部手机，对吗？
This data is a little bit old.
这些数据有点旧了。
And all of those, all the phones are connected.
而且所有这些，所有的手机都已连接。
So you have 4 billion, this kind of very powerful devices at the end of the day, which are connected,
所以你最终拥有了40亿台非常强大的设备，它们都连接在一起。
right?
对吗？
So you have everything.
所以你有一切。
You have a huge range, right?
你们有很大的产品范围，对吗？
You have everything from data center, which hundreds of thousands of computers to sensor
你拥有从数以十万计的计算机到传感器的一切数据中心。
networks, right?
是的，网络。
Which you may not be even able to see these chips, right?
你可能甚至看不到这些芯片，对吗？
And everything in between, right?
对，包括中间的一切，对吗？
And different workloads.
和不同的工作量。
And just to drive home the point and I'll here, so just like I mentioned earlier, many
而且为了强调这一点，我在这里，就像我之前提到的一样，很多...
of the applications you are using today, they are distributed, right?
你今天使用的应用程序都是分布式的，对吗？
Facebook, Twitter, and so forth.
Facebook, Twitter,等等。
And this is what happens under the hood, right?
是的，这就是发生在引擎盖下的情况，对吗？
And let's say you do a simple search, right?
然后假设你进行了一个简单的搜索，对吗？
From your Android 4 or iPhone, right?
是的，我可以从Android 4或iPhone上进行翻译。
What do you do?
你做什么工作？
So first of all, you need to figure out what backend, what servers you need to connect
首先，你需要弄清楚你需要连接哪些后端和服务器。
to, to get, to send the request, your search request, and to get the answer.
去，获取，发送请求，你的搜索请求，以及获取答案。
In order to do that, you need to do this DNS request, domain name service, right?
为了做到这一点，你需要进行这个DNS请求，域名服务，对吗？
And this is, you know, it's like you need to resolve, use this link, right?
这个，你知道的，就是你需要解决的问题，使用这个链接，对吧？
It's google.com to a particular server, right?
是的，它是将google.com发送到特定的服务器，对吗？
So you have an entire domain DNS infrastructure, which consisting of many servers, and they
是的，您拥有一个完整的域名系统（DNS）基础架构，由许多服务器组成。
will cooperate to give you an answer to tell you who you need to connect to, who you need
合作以告诉你需要联系的人，你需要什么答案。
to send the packets.
发送数据包。
Now, so once you get that address, which is an IP address, you are going to send it over
现在，一旦你获得了那个地址，也就是一个IP地址，你就会将它发送出去。
the internet, right?
互联网，对吗？
Over the internet, these packets are going to be routed by switches, routers, and so
通过互联网，这些数据包将会通过交换机、路由器等设备进行路由。
forth.
前进。
And it's going to go, based on the IP address, probably in a data center, they are going
而且根据IP地址来看，它很可能位于一个数据中心，它们正在去的地方。
to land to a load balancer.
将流量导向负载均衡器。
The load balancer, you get the packets, you send to a server, the web server probably.
负载均衡器，你接收数据包，然后将其发送给一个服务器，可能是Web服务器。
The web server is going to look at the request and based on the request, it's going to send,
网络服务器将会查看请求，并根据请求发送。
you know, request an entire other system to resolve that request, right?
你知道，请求一个完全不同的系统来解决那个请求，对吧？
To give you the answers if you have a Google query.
如果你有一个谷歌查询，我可以给你答案。
And obviously, you may also have to get some ads in the process.
显然，你在这个过程中可能还需要一些广告。
You have another infrastructure doing only that, figuring out what ads to show.
你有另一个基础设施专门负责这个，找出要展示哪些广告。
And then you need to put together the entire page and send it back and to be displayed
然后你需要将整个页面组合起来并发送回去以供展示。
on your computer, right?
在你的电脑上，对吗？
So this is just to give you a sense how complicated things are.
所以这只是为了让你了解事情有多复杂。
And all of these interactions are handled by the operating system, right, at the low
是的，所有这些交互都由操作系统处理，对吗，在底层。
level.
水平。
So let me just, we have only five minutes.
好的，让我看看，我们只有五分钟。
So what I'm going to do, I'm going to do the following thing and we are going to continue
那么我要做的是，我要做以下的事情，然后我们会继续。
next time.
下次。
Let me first try to answer some of the questions and then I'm going to go straight to some
让我先试着回答一些问题，然后我会直接进入一些其他的话题。
logistics.
物流。
How low level does this class get?
这个类有多底层？
Do we talk about things like pipelining?
我们是在讨论像流水线这样的事情吗？
We won't talk much about like pipelining, if you are referring at the CPU process, in
我们不会过多讨论流水线技术，如果你指的是CPU的处理过程的话。
the CPU pipelining, like instruction pipelining.
CPU流水线，如指令流水线。
We are not going to talk.
我们不打算谈话。
We are going to talk a little bit about hyper-threading.
我们要稍微谈一下超线程技术。
We are going to talk about that.
我们将要讨论这个。
So we'll answer, so this is about hyper-threading.
所以我们会回答，这是关于超线程的问题。
We are going to talk more about, in short, it's a way in which you can share the core,
我们将会更多地讨论，简而言之，这是一种你可以分享核心的方式。
one core between two threads, which can come from different applications.
一个核心在两个线程之间，这两个线程可以来自不同的应用程序。
So it's multiplexing one core.
所以它是将一个核心进行多路复用。
Okay, so yeah.
好的，是的。
Okay, so let me just skip and obviously we'll do the rest next time and talk a little bit
好的，那么让我跳过一些，显然我们下次会完成剩下的，现在我们聊一下。
here about, more about the class.
这里是关于课程的更多信息。
Okay, syllabus and it's online.
好的，教学大纲已经上传到网上了。
You have the class.
你有课。
So we are going to obviously to learn the operating system concepts and how a system
所以我们显然要学习操作系统的概念以及系统的运行方式。
programmer is going to use these concepts.
程序员将要使用这些概念。
What are the interfaces, APIs, and then we are going to learn about how the operating
什么是接口、API，然后我们将学习操作系统的工作原理。
system implements some of this functionality.
系统实现了部分功能。
Like how is it going to manage concurrency, multiple applications accessing shared resources
并发管理是如何进行的？多个应用程序如何访问共享资源？
at the same time.
同时。
Address space, how you are going to provide isolation between different applications so
地址空间，你将如何在不同应用程序之间提供隔离？
that each one application or process will not step over the memory of another application
每个应用程序或进程都不会超出其他应用程序的内存限制。
or process.
或者处理。
File systems, how you are going to access and store the data and retrieve the data,
文件系统，是指如何访问、存储和检索数据的方式。
send the data and receive the data over the network.
发送数据并通过网络接收数据。
We are going to talk a little bit about distributed systems and the protocols, which are, and
我们要稍微谈一下分布式系统和协议，它们是什么，
the mechanisms which are implemented by distributed systems to make them easier to use and to
分布式系统实施的机制旨在使其更易于使用和管理。
be more efficient.
更高效。
And we are going to talk about reliability and security, fault tolerance protection and
我们将讨论可靠性和安全性，容错保护和
so forth.
等等。
And finally, we are going to talk about a little bit about cloud infrastructure, which
最后，我们要稍微谈一下云基础设施，它
is very relevant because right now, cloud is a de facto standard.
非常相关，因为现在云已经成为事实上的标准。
Many companies are building, especially startups are building their application.
许多公司正在建设应用程序，尤其是初创公司正在建设他们的应用程序。
This class is hands-on.
这个课程是实践性的。
You are going to learn by doing.
你将通过实践学习。
You have a bunch of homeworks and projects.
你有一堆作业和项目。
Projects are extremely important.
项目非常重要。
And with the projects you are going to implement actually also is the homework, some mechanism,
而且你要实施的项目实际上也是作业，一些机制，
some functionality that operating system do.
操作系统的一些功能包括：管理计算机的硬件和软件资源、提供用户界面、调度任务和进程、管理文件和存储、提供网络连接、实施安全措施、处理错误和异常、提供系统服务等。
Like your stress and scheduling, file systems and so forth.
像你的压力和日程安排，文件系统等等。
Memory allocation.
内存分配。
This will be very, very exciting.
这将会非常非常令人兴奋。
Now what are the demands?
现在有什么要求？
The project will require you to be very comfortable with programming and debugging C. So remember,
这个项目需要你对C语言编程和调试非常熟悉。所以记住，
recall pointers, memory management, use GDB for debugging.
回忆指针，内存管理，使用GDB进行调试。
So just go over 61C again.
那就再复习一下61C吧。
And you need to know how to use Git for version control.
你需要知道如何使用Git进行版本控制。
And there is a C programming reference here if you need.
如果你需要的话，这里有一个C编程的参考资料。
So please consult that.
所以请咨询一下。
I think the first two sections are dedicated to programming and debugging reviews.
我认为前两个部分是关于编程和调试的评论。
So please attend these sections.
所以请参加这些部分。
And you can attend any two section, I believe, for the first two weeks.
你可以参加任意两个部分，我相信，在前两周内。
After that, you need to choose one section.
之后，你需要选择一个部分。
The other thing I want to say, and to be quick here, but also I want to emphasize that projects
另外一件我想说的事情，希望能够快点说完，但我也想强调的是项目
are very important.
非常重要。
And projects are not only about doing a piece of software and building a piece of software,
而项目不仅仅是关于开发和构建软件，
a project about teaching you how to collaborate, how to work in a team.
一个关于教你如何合作、如何在团队中工作的项目。
This will be extremely important for you.
这对你来说将非常重要。
If you go and to be a software engineer, this is a key skill you need to learn.
如果你选择成为一名软件工程师，这是你需要学习的关键技能。
You are going to learn to work in a team.
你将学会在团队中工作。
You need to make the team successful because that's how you are going to become successful.
你需要让团队成功，因为这样你才能够变得成功。
You are not going to work alone.
你不会独自工作。
We require the project to have four members, number five.
我们要求项目有四个成员，第五个。
And the exception will be very rare.
而且例外情况将非常罕见。
Please, this is pandemic, still pandemic.
请注意，这是一场大流行病，仍然是一场大流行病。
It's very hard.
非常困难。
Most of the activities will be online.
大部分活动将在线进行。
If you do online, turn the camera on.
如果你在线上，打开摄像头。
Try to emulate the physical presence as much as possible.
尽可能地模拟真实的存在感。
But also now you can also, the campus is open.
但现在你也可以，校园已经开放了。
You know, if you feel comfortable, you can go and meet in person.
你知道，如果你感觉舒服的话，你可以去见面。
But collaborate, collaborate, collaborate.
但是合作，合作，合作。
And also not only between you and your members of the team, but also your TA.
还有不仅仅是你和你的团队成员之间，还有你的助教。
Overcommunication is how you make this project successful.
过度沟通是使这个项目成功的方式。
Then you need to devise the work among the members of the team to require both decision
然后你需要将工作分配给团队成员，需要他们做出决策。
and additional collaboration because you are going to depend on the work of other people
并且需要额外的合作，因为你将依赖其他人的工作。
do in your team.
你在你的团队中做什么？
This is a grading, 36% is for three midterms.
这是一个分数评定，36%是三次期中考试的成绩。
We have only midterms, no final.
我们只有期中考试，没有期末考试。
36% projects, 80% homework, 10% participation, section, lectures, and so forth.
36%的项目，80%的作业，10%的参与度，小组讨论，课堂讲座等等。
You'll hear more about the project.
你会听到更多关于这个项目的消息。
You'll have a design document.
你将会有一个设计文档。
Design document will be due.
设计文档将到期。
You are going to get feedback from the TAs and so forth.
你将会从助教等人那里得到反馈。
Books and infrastructures.
书籍和基础设施。
You should be able to find all the information.
你应该能够找到所有的信息。
There's a class web page.
有一个班级网页。
There is a Piazza.
有一个Piazza。
You find the link to the Piazza as well there.
你可以在那里找到Piazza的链接。
The lectures will be recorded.
这些讲座将会被录制下来。
Yeah, sorry about today, about the beginning of the lecture.
是的，对不起，对于今天，对于讲座的开始。
The textbook is the operating system principles and practice from Tom Anderson and Mike Dalin.
这本教科书是由Tom Anderson和Mike Dalin撰写的操作系统原理与实践。
And there are a few other books, very good.
还有几本其他的书，非常好。
And you are encouraged to consult and you can refer to.
你被鼓励咨询和参考。
And we are going to have a few supplemental materials, a few research papers and so forth.
我们还会提供一些补充材料，一些研究论文之类的。
We are going to let you know.
我们会通知你。
Finally, please, it's like, this is not a joke.
最后，请，请，就像，这不是一个笑话。
Personal integrity, you signed the UCB Academy Honor Code.
个人诚信，您已签署了UCB学院的荣誉守则。
So please live by it.
那么请按照这个原则生活。
You can explain the concept of other people in the group.
你可以解释一下群体中其他人的概念。
You can discuss the concept with other people on the group.
你可以在群组中与其他人讨论这个概念。
You can even help your friend to debug your code, the code.
你甚至可以帮助你的朋友调试你的代码，这段代码。
Or you can search online for generic codes.
或者你可以在网上搜索通用代码。
This is good, but you cannot share the code with other groups.
这是很好的，但是你不能与其他组分享代码。
You cannot copy or read another group's code or test cases.
你不能复制或阅读其他小组的代码或测试用例。
You cannot copy or reading online code or test cases from prior years.
你不能复制或阅读以往年份的在线代码或测试用例。
And we are going, as you know that, we compare all project submission against prior year
我们会进行比较，正如你所知道的，我们会将所有项目提交与去年进行对比。
submissions and online solutions and will take actions right against your funder.
提交和在线解决方案，并将采取行动对付您的资助者。
So please don't do that.
所以请不要这样做。
It's not going to help you with learning.
这不会帮助你学习。
That's probably the most important reason you shouldn't do it.
那可能是你不应该做的最重要的原因。
Let's try hard to make this class and to keep this class interactive.
让我们努力使这堂课变得有趣并保持互动。
And I'm going to stop here.
我要在这里停下来。
I'm going to take it about the talk, obviously, a little bit more about the operating system
我将要谈一下，显然，更多关于操作系统的内容。
general overview next time.
下次请给一个总体概述。
And now let me answer the questions which are still here.
现在让我来回答这些仍然存在的问题。
So there are two other questions.
所以还有两个其他问题。
There is actually one last question.
实际上还有一个最后的问题。
Will it be good to review material of the later half of 6.1c like cache?
对于复习6.1c后半部分的内容，比如缓存，会有好处吗？
Yes, absolutely.
是的，绝对没问题。
Components of the CPU, how much of this?
CPU的组成部分，有多少种？
Yes, absolutely.
是的，绝对可以。
This will be very useful.
这将非常有用。
We are going to talk about caching.
我们将要讨论缓存。
We are going to talk and reviewing that it will be so useful.
我们将要讨论和回顾，这将会非常有用。
How does participation grading work?
参与度评分是如何工作的？
This will be mostly because it will be smaller groups from interacting with your TAs, office
这主要是因为与您的助教、办公室互动的小组会更小。
hours and discussion sections.
小时和讨论部分。
I am, at the size of this class, I don't think I will have the opportunity to interact with
我在这个班级的规模下，我觉得我不会有机会与其他人互动。
many of you, especially since we are remote.
你们中的很多人，尤其是因为我们是远程的。
But obviously, if you have any problem, anything, please do not hesitate to drop me an email
但是显然，如果你有任何问题，任何事情，请不要犹豫给我发邮件。
and you can look for me.
你可以找我。
I'll be in soda, soda hall, at least now and then.
我会在苏打大厅，至少偶尔会去。
So thank you so much, everyone.
非常感谢大家。
And I'll see you next Tuesday.
我下周二见你。
And if you have any other questions, please ask the questions.
如果你有任何其他问题，请提出来。
And if you also have any other suggestions about how to make the class better, more interactive,
如果你还有关于如何让课堂更好、更互动的其他建议，
please do not hesitate to let us know.
请不要犹豫，告诉我们。
It's again, the first time I'm using the webinar and it's not a lot of, you know, it's hard
这是我第一次使用网络研讨会，而且并不是很顺利，你知道的，很困难。
to just talk at the screen and see the slide, not see any of your faces.
只是在屏幕上讲话，看幻灯片，不看你们的任何面孔。
So but, you know, let's try to do our best.
所以，你知道的，让我们尽力而为吧。
And yeah, any idea you see, you have to improve interactivity, to improve the class in general,
而且，你看到的任何想法，都需要提高互动性，以改善整个课堂。
let us know.
让我们知道。
Thank you.
谢谢你。
[ Applause ]
[鼓掌]